so this is The Suitor on the eight
thoughts of a great person
what sort of that
and go to nikaya 8.30
and so on one occasion Venable anuruda
alone in seclusion contemplated the
following
the following eighth thought of a great
person seven
you can't play any seven
and number one is this Dumber
is for I'll just read all seven and we
can discuss it later this dummies is for
one who is not seeking admiration
not for one who is seeking admiration
this dhamma is for one who is content
not for one who is discontent
this dummies one is for one who resorts
to seclusion not for one who Delights in
society this dhama is for one who is diligent
this dhama is for one who is diligent
not for one who is lazy
this time is for one who has a good
memory not who is forgetful
not who is forgetful
as dhamma is for one who is settled not
for one who is unsettled this dummy is
for one who is wise not for one who is
foolish and as he was thinking these thoughts
and as he was thinking these thoughts
the blessed one knew what was in the
mind of Venable anawooda
and then said to him
it is commendable that you have
reflected on these thoughts of a great
person therefore
therefore
also reflect on this eighth thought of a
great person
this dhamma is for one who Delights in
non-proliferation not for one who
Delights in proliferation
so just to just to add the
the Buddhist says further that when you
reflect on these eight thoughts
then you will be able to attain As You
Wish vagina's
or for Giants
and when you do that then
all of the requisites basic requisites
you know so
uh alms just you know rough arm through
rough clothes
rough shelter rough medicine
will feel like luxuries
so just keep that in mind that there's
these thinking these thoughts leads to
Janna and pleasant abiding with basic
requisites the basic of the basic
the roughest of the rough
and so the the Buddha goes on further
and describes each of these points
so what was meant by the statement this
dhamma is for those
uh who are not seeking admiration those
who are not
uh
who are not seeking admiration
but it's usually translated as this dumb
is for one who who has no desires
few desires few desires but the next
point is one who is content who is
contained little so it's like the same
but the Pali word is it means
unassuming and
and
you could say
one who is uh not pretentious
and the explanation that the Buddha
gives says here when a biku is one who doesn't
says here when a biku is one who doesn't
seek admiration
he does not wish let other people know
me to be one who doesn't seek admiration
when he is content he doesn't wish let
other people know me as content when he
is in solitude he doesn't wish that
people know me to be one who resorts to
Solitude when he's diligent he does not
wish that other people know me to be
diligent when he is
when he is
recollected mindful he does not wish let
other people know me to be recollected
when he's settled he doesn't wish for
others to know him has settled when he
is wise he doesn't wish others to know
him as wise and when he is
non-proliferated he doesn't wish others
to know that he is not proliferated
hmm so he doesn't
so he doesn't
go around seeking admiration
Desiring to be known
the desire and pretentiousness the
dictionary attempting to impress by
affecting a greater importance or Merit
than is actually possessed
yeah that's why that's a bit too coarse
yeah but pretentiousness but um
you could see just to the point of not
not it's not like oh I I want to be not
known but it's certainly on the level of
I well I don't want to be known either
because sometimes people can think in
order to be humble and unassuming and
not seeking admiration I must seek the
opposite that's not the case either so
you simply practices
out of his own wisdom for his own
benefit whether others know him on
account of it or not it's irrelevant he
Bears no relevant it's not a reference
point for him
so he doesn't wish to be known that
doesn't mean he will prevent to be known
if others do know him on the on on their
own accord like he would go out of his
way to hide himself or something like
that that's not the case either because
you would do that because you still care
now you just go the other way
so that's why it's the it's the it's
like obviously the
suckless thread that goes from the most
coarse um pretentiousness
um pretentiousness
uh pompousness
admiration to just
do you have perception of others in
value in the perception of others
knowing what you're doing
like because there doesn't need to be
any value in that it's relevant in other
words so if you're doing it you're doing it
so if you're doing it you're doing it
for the sake of practice for the sake of
benefit for the sake of like
settlement and all the other things that
follow um so but then what if your mind still
um so but then what if your mind still
thinks about whether others know you or
not it still values a degree of admiration
it still values a degree of admiration
how do you deal with that I mean
I mean
the fundamental issue with that is
is the other is is as long as there is
this sense of self there will be the
other yeah yeah that's why it is there
but that's not the question the question
is how do you deal with that which is
there how do you reverting the sense of
self would be but how can you uproot it
if you're still admiring others or
you're seeking the admiration yes so
that you start by seeking admiration
how do you approve it because seeking a
mediation maintains that which you're
trying to approve so by seeing that
seeking but and thereby not being moved
by it's not being
pressured by it
you you only get it's not a matter of
choice though isn't it not being
pressured by it you are oh sorry you're
not acting out of it not acting out of
it that's the point so seeking
admiration how is that done well it's done by
how is that done well it's done by
acting out of that wanting a mediation
so the Mind might still value others
knowing this but are you seeking it are
you acting out of it are you making
others known are you hinting so that you
are known as such and such all of those
are intentional actions efforts that you
make so don't do that
and then if the mind is still seeking
admiration well that's fine you endure
that part you don't act out of it you
don't add fuel to it in terms of your
choices and actions they would then be
contributing to that need for admiration
and by not fueling it and carrying on
practicing putting it aside that which
pressures you to act out of uh it will
subside you will stop valuing it you will then
you will stop valuing it you will then
one day just find yourself oh I stopped
caring whether others know or not
but you won't stop caring magically or
on account of some sort of
um specific thing to do it's more like
no you have to have endure that pressure
for admiration for recognition
sufficiently enough and not having acted
out of it not feeling justified in
acting out of it not fueling it further
um and then if others know you're not if
they admire you or not that's not a
problem I mean praise and blame it's what moves
I mean praise and blame it's what moves
the entire world to one of the worldly
wins so it's a deeply rooted thing
being praised being blamed is
irrationally feared being praised is
irrationally liked and so it's not just
something you can choose to not be
affected by
but how do you go beyond it that's the
question and the question the answer to
that is just as we said well first don't
act out of it so same if you're blamed
well don't act out of it immediately
like don't like however let me explain
myself why is that rooted in fear of
being blamed
or what difference does it make like
even if say well I'm playing wrongly
yeah but did you do something wrong no
well then you don't need to explain
yourself the only reason you would be
explaining yourself is because you don't
like being blamed regardless of whether
it's righteous blame or not so you're
acting our weakness you're not settled
you're not wise you are fueling it
further you're fueling your dependence
on irrational wins of the world how they
move uh same do you
um relish the praise
to Incline towards you to welcome it to
Delight in it exactly like you would do
to Central thoughts
part of that o is this
this
you know when you're blamed not
necessarily by everybody but certainly
by certain people
um you start kind of from the point of
view of actually kind of
if I'm blamed by by somebody whose let's
say opinion I respect that means I am
blameworthy as in you've kind of almost
defined your your own sense of right and
wrong in terms of how others
see you yeah and saying like when when
you're praised the reason people kind of
it's so kind of intoxicating is that
that means I'm good yeah like I'm
objectively good
because other senior is good because
I've been praised yeah so yeah that's
like drama is not for that kind of
person no no that needs to you don't
know what is good you have to have
endured that quite a lot if you if
you're still moved by on that level I
mean you're not authentic enough so but
that is a practice already yeah and
during it on the right level
um then yes as I said if you're blamed
you look above four is it factual
is it actions that have been rooted in
which case sure you may commence to that
extent but even then you will pretty quickly
but even then you will pretty quickly
recognize if you are acting out of it
because irrationally you just
resist the discomfort of blame just that
doesn't matter it doesn't matter who
doesn't matter if somebody respects you
or not
basically if people blame you that must
be avoided because for no for no other
reason simply because it's unpleasant
and that's for for as long as you act
out of those things or try to avoid or
prevent or kind of
um Wiggle out you will also then be
cultivating the the opposite of it which
is you will be gratuitously still
valuing praise for no reason
for notepad and if there is a factual
reason well the factory of that phrase
is what matters not whether somebody
praised you about it or not that's
irrelevant so if somebody prays you because you're
so if somebody prays you because you're
so wise well it's your wisdom that
matters there not the fact that somebody
praised you they did not make it more
palpable or or more valuable and you you
will start to differentiate it and then
whether they praise your blame you know
you know where the line for what's good
and what's bad is
what's blameworthy you would see within
yourself
there's that that's that danger of
praise danger of Praise because it's so easily
danger of Praise because it's so easily
it's intoxicated yeah in the start you
don't have any wisdom yeah so you get
praise from the start
yeah if you're not authentic enough yes
it would be a very easy and slippery
yeah you get ordained yeah you become
Praises in our hunt almost immediately
in some you know some cultures
everyone's bowing down to so wow
and now you're going to do the work when
you're already the whole world but most
importantly really you are praised if
you you know
told the line of the established
tradition for example so you're praised
on a kind of external conformity
so that does like you know whether
somebody is elevated but people bow to
them or not that's you know it's a big
course I think most people wouldn't
would see the line there are it's just a
traditional thing whatever but where
people would not see the line is
uh emulating the external form parents
tradition etiquette
for accomplishment
so now if I actually meet these
requirements of external behavior that
is that is what is good
in and of itself and that is
praiseworthy in and of itself if I thus
don't meet these equally kind of
pointless often pointless requirements
or that is blame worthy so basically by
developing that attitude uh you are
completely obscured in the domain of
intentions which are the root factor of
whether something is actually
praiseworthy of blame or blame body so
if you have committed to such an
external etiquette Norm practice tradition
etiquette Norm practice tradition
observances authorities
it will result in you being absolutely
convinced now that you are pure and
praiseworthy and and upholding the
dhamma while you're actually even more
you have drifted even more further away
from basic recognition of your
intentionality behind everything you do
which you were probably closer to when
you started practicing than you are now
so it's not like how I do it and how
it's why am I doing it
grid aversion or distraction or non-grid
non-version of distraction that is the
criteria but that's not something that
can be measured as easily as a perfect
mode of comportment
that people are you speak so softly he
never raises his voice he moves his
hands slowly
he whispers he floats in the air that is
praiseworthy well not according to the
suitors because the Buddha did the
number of passages mentioned there was
that whole if you might have a companion
in a holy life that is softly spoken
friendly praised by everybody lovely to
be with amazing company just so gentle
in every way but of a wrong View and you
should avoid him as you would avoid the
charcoal pit because it's just no that's
not what you're practicing here then you
can have a holy companion who is rough
hard to listen to hard to live with
difficult person but is override view oh
you should then make the effort and
endure that and live with them because
you can actually learn
but if the entire
if all of us are only Guided by the
external norm and comportment and and
right branding of right words then yes
others will praise us on account of it
and then if you don't meet the
requirements you'll be blamed on a
conflict but neither of those things
really matter for where the practices
and where the intentions are
so it's not like you need to now resist
and reject all the conventions and so on
there will be equally misguided but you
certainly need to start really
recognizing what is the source of of an
action that makes it either praiseworld
your blame word regardless of whether
rather praise you an account with or
blame you in account of it so now you
have many different stuff many different
Traditions many different schools many
different branches observation many
different interpretations and all this
in other words things have proliferated
so there is no more a unified even
external criteria I mean you can use
common sense but as I said people tend
to subjugate the common sense to the
whether this is praised or blamed by the
general population of spiritual
practitioners if they like it I should
do it if they don't like it I should not
do it
but that's only a relative criteria you
should be considering internally it
should be rooted in where is my
intention behind this that's what makes
it good that's what makes you bad if you
were to ask most people today they would
say no I've we think you should not be
celibate and sense restraint that's too
much that's a depression that's bad for
the mind you should practice your
spirituality without that
so would you would you then just draw a
line there or so where do you draw a
line what is the line
or if the tradition requires you to
spend you know all the time in like a
massive groups of people hundreds of
monks thousands of laities for days or
just constant I mean they would have
told off
for gathering together and talking over
sowing like patching robes and stuff he
said is this like a fisherman's market
but today it's deemed acceptable that
thousands of Us come together for days
and you just just eat and talk and sit
and bless and it's regarded as a wholly
Noble thing to do
because everybody likes it it's like but
is that the criteria
if it's universally praised is that why
is this good because you could find
plenty of other things at the university
place that you know you won't be doing
so and that's the whole point once you
start clarifying that thread between
praise and blame and admiration and no
well if you follow that thread all the way as
if you follow that thread all the way as
it takes you you will abandon any and
every conceit internally or externally
any sense of self internally or
externally so it wouldn't be that
surprising or or mystical or magical how
you would then abide in Jannah at will
because it's not just mere reasoning
sure you can reason but then follow the
same thread all the way
and anything that partakes in the uh in
the conceit in the admiration you don't
act out of it it doesn't matter if the
whole world says no no you should do it
venerable sir it is good
you know that it's not because you now
see a direct reference uh point for
whether it's good or not which is your
intention and tension for admiration or
intention that dismisses it and doesn't
want anything to do with it do not
pressured you're not acting out of the
pressure of the world yeah and that's
that's the way to basically to reach
this point to start recognizing this
subtle subtle thread is to yeah and due
the pressure of of Praise of tradition
of external requirements you know the
precepts you're not vinaya you know the
sense of strength you know the sutures
you don't need any other authority you
don't need any other if you need other
things to keep you together as a monk
you better start you know
Praise of others to keep you together or
the or the like uniformity of the
tradition or something
oh because without it I just can't do it
myself well means you can't practice
yourself and practice is for oneself so
in other words for as long as you're
doing it you won't be practicing it
there's like this
where this says like the way to
self-effacement is
yeah or just to reflect what others may
be cruel because here I won't be cruel
others may have wrong whatever but here
like whatever the world does yeah is
irrelevant I'm alone actually I'm alone
and I'm taking that on and that's where
the practice is and that is how you
would then yeah
it kind of ties into that other one he
he Delights in
Solitude not in society in company in
the ways of society in just the views of
society yeah
like that about the wrong reasons to go
forth like one goes forth and then
against the Renown and fame and he is
contented with that and that's where he
stops and that's not why
it just reminds me of another Suitor I
can just turn that one for uh-huh
uh it's dig inikaya one
says oh yeah yeah if because others
speak in this Praise of me or in the
space of a dhamma or the Sangha you
should not give way to resentment
displeasure or
animosity against them for if you were
to become angry upset in such a
situation you would would only be
creating an obstacle for yourself if you
become angry or upset when others speak
in this praise
of us would you be able to recognize
whether their statements are right or
wrong yeah certainly not Lord
and if other speaking displays of me the
Dumber or the Sangha you should unravel
what is false and point out
which is false saying for such and such
a reason this is wrong this is untrue
there is no such thing in this this is
not found Among Us and if others
speaking Praise of me the dumb of the
Sangha you should not give way to
Elation Joy
and happiness for it if you were to
become excited in such a way
you would only be creating an obstacle
for yourself if others speak in Praise
of me the dumb or the Sangha you should
acknowledge what is in fact true
for such and such a reason this is a
fact this is true that there is such a
thing in us this is found Among Us
and he goes on further to say it is only
in regard to insignificant matters and
Minor Details of mere moral virtue that
wielding an ordinary person would refer
when speaking in Praise of the Buddha [Music]
[Music]
yeah but the bottom line is see either
way you don't make it personal by acting
out of your own
personality so to speak or you are you
are related or you are upset so now
you're referring addressing dealing with the
referring addressing dealing with the
other person that said that or did that
no just point out what is factually
wrong of you as a wrong View
or what is the right aspect of what they
said as a right aspect
it doesn't need to go it doesn't need to
become personal either way he doesn't
need to go further than that
what was said is factually wrong because
of this this and this and yeah this was
that was correct because of this this
and this I don't really care who said it
why they said it and you know what type
of person what kind person they are and
so on it's irrelevant
if it is relevant is because you have
taken it personally and if you take it
personally does that mean
can you take things personally and have
perspective at the same time on things
that you take in person no but taking
things personally means automatically
losing a degree of perspective and then
you will not be able to see whether
they're factually objectively right or
wrong in what they're saying
so that's why it's an obstacle you are
you are creating an obstruction for
yourself unnecessarily because there's
no reason to take it personal you just
did it out of that
unchecked habits acting out of it and
not wanting to endure the discomfort of
that pressure
oh but he he was attacking me he was
talking about me yeah and even imagine
the worst case scenario yes he was he is
disrespecting you nobody else
why is that your problem
oh I don't quite know he just feels
uncomfortable I just take that painful
feeling for granted and I want to get
rid of it or something
or something
or by not taking yourself sir yeah well
that's one way to try to get rid of it
but have you freed yourself from it in
the past whenever you defended your
honor and Justified yourself and showed
everybody that they were wrong and you
were right
well no I'm still here equally affected
and again that's why the Buddha did
compare enduring the words of others to
just putting up and bearing the elements
like it's going to be felt uncomfortably
because of your personality concede
still there degrees of it not because
you know it's a problem in and of itself
but if and if someone was blaming you
for something you could actually well by
not acting personally but not taking
personally then you would actually be
able to see
impersonally whether the blame is
factually correct maybe maybe you have
been doing something wrong and now you
have a chance to and now you see it yeah
and you still don't need to take it
personal and that's why you would be
able to see this and actually Rectify it
yes making what is right and what is
wrong more important than yourself yeah
and everybody that's the thing with that
everybody kind of already knows that
even the completed
say somebody wants to sort out their
life you know
maybe draw a line for for people they're
taking advantage of them maybe draw a
line for themselves if you were to ask
them in that like a a non-imperative sense
in that like a a non-imperative sense
what do you think you should do
they would probably 99 of them would
know exactly what they need to do to
make their life better and their mind
calmer and more settled
but then they won't be able to do it
because they will still put the
personality first which then it would
also then require it will be hard to
uphold these determinations these
decisions these knowledges of what you
need to do because it's just I'm just so
used to acting out of the pressure of
Senses sensuality personality and the
views this is just too abstract although
factually I know what I need to do to
make my life better I know where the
line is where I should draw it where I
should say no to people and so on
but I just can't
I said well that's why like if you can't
do even that then you you want you know
the dhamma simply doesn't apply to you
just another Suitor which might
correspond to this
as the four types of people with no
integrity and
with Integrity uh
so the dumb is not for one with no
integrity
and this shooter says
person of knowing Integrity when unasked
reveals his own good points to say
nothing of when asked
furthermore when asked when pressed with
questions he is one who speaks of his
own good points in full and in detail
without missions without holding back
this person you may know this printable
one is a person of no integrity
in other words he speaks about himself
yeah just thinks about himself yeah well let
just thinks about himself yeah well let
me teach you the Dharma by speaking
about myself
as a child I was like this well whatever
whichever way shape and form Dad can
take you could see where the emphasis is
is it on the points made
uh freedom from contradiction Clarity of
instruction or is it on I've been
through these experiences I have done
this I've seen this I've completely
unnecessary even if it were factual but
then if it were factual you wouldn't be
emphasizing yourself well yeah it's as
simple as that
the other side of it says he is one who
speaks of his own if he's asked and
pressed he speaks of his own good points
not in full not in detail with the
missions holding back
so if he's pressed
even if he's pressed see if he's asked
okay
because yeah obviously it's it's all
about yourself
we're coming across for you you want
other peoples to know you as yeah
someone great
to partake in your love for yourself
basically I want others to love me as
much as I love myself
so the second point
uh this dumb is for one who is content
not for one who is discontent
and
this means that his content with any
kind of requisites robes Elmsford
lodgings and medicine and you can take
that same principle so again take that
thread as far as he goes and my content
remember this content
so what is the what is this contentment
when is a person discontent
exactly yeah so it's not like
necessarily um you know this content by by being in
um you know this content by by being in
a bad mood for example
you are responsible
for your discontent and then sure you
can be in a bad mood in account of that
but today's content is yeah so I
am cultivating
welcoming the lighting and so on acting
out of the attitude of
oh it shouldn't be this way I wanted
certain other way or I don't want it now
or I didn't have enough of it so a
certain degree of entitlement
righteousness all that would make you discontent
all that would make you discontent
wanting one thing basically what you
don't have
wanting more of what you have wanting
the external world to be a certain way
wanting the external world to be a
certain way just whenever there is a
discontent you will you will find it in
one of these one of these ways if you're
going about it so you are responsible
for it directly that's why if you then
abandon that
and cultivate the contentment with
whichever way like
um your situation is
then you you will actually follow again
that thread as far as it goes and it
would result in in kind of pretty much
completely uprooting sensuality
if you if you follow the the threat of
contentment with any any condition of
the body any requisites any access no
sense of removal of the slightest sense
of entitlement that's why
I think discontent was one of the mata's
daughters discontent sensuality
discontent sensuality
goes hand in hand
it's rooted in desires
it's interesting like
because it's kind of obvious that
contentments like which is more pleasant
contentment or discontent yeah it's
obvious that contentment is more
pleasant but it's not the kind of
pleasure already depends on the level of
the kind of pleasure that people well
that's exactly the the the principle
sensuality exactly so then in and of
itself the prospect of centrality is actually
the prospect of centrality is actually
unpleasant to realize I would be more
contented if I don't act out of this if
this leaves me alone if I don't make
this worse that is more
contenting for myself
but that already requires recognition
and wisdom and discernment of uh well of
certainly of the nature of sensuality to
a great degree
because otherwise your assumptions are
on the level no no contentment comes
after I get what I want here
so the only purpose of that wanting is
more wanting if you look at it from this
yeah from but from the individual point
of view I can't see that yeah you won't
be seeing that so then the only purpose
of well basically the only idea of
contentment is the contentment on
account of centrality that you know
which means anything less than your
desires being met
uh will be experiences this content so
you're seeing
yeah it's tricking you the centrality into
it's tricking you the centrality into
seeing discontent as content as as
something which is yeah yeah just
delightful yeah it is a version of
perception yeah that which is actually
discontent you're perceiving is content
there it is actually painful you're
perceiving is Pleasant it's agreeable
whereas if you were to see it then you
would just endure this already given
desire which is painful and and
therefore yeah be able to maintain this
perspective and not fuel it and that's
the that's the only way yeah for it to
and then there's even the pressure of it
would eventually
disappear yeah and then you wouldn't
need to even endure anything yeah
already be content yeah exactly yeah the
wounds healed no matter what touches it
it doesn't hurt anymore yeah so no
external thinking give you that no no no
more prod you know the best meal with
just a month yeah perfect amount of salt
yeah it's not seen there anymore
becomes irrelevant basically
whether people praise you or blame you
doesn't matter and the third point
this time is for one who resorts to
Solitude not for one who Delights in
society and what does that mean when a bigger
and what does that mean when a bigger
resorts to solitude
other bikers bikunis male layoff
followers female they followers Kings
Royal ministers heads of other
religions and disciples belonging to
other religions approaching
in each case with a mind that inclines
to seclusion withdrawn
the lighting and renunciation he gives
them a talk concerned invariably
concerned with dismissing them
so he doesn't get involved
only so much so that they
can well they answer what they came for
but they don't make them stay longer you
know chatting them up but uh and so on
and that would come out of her mind that
inclines towards Solitude you can try
and measure and learn how to speak but
fundamentally are you delighting in
company or are you content being alone
because see all of these thoughts it's
on the level of something you are
cultivating or not
that's why if you cultivate him rightly
wisdom will be the result of it and and
Janus will be obtainable at will
so
is your mind inclining to a Solitude or
to its others spending time with others
talking with others seeing us
and sure you will not start nobody will
start suddenly oh I prefer solitude
so that's why it takes effort and
discernment but then yes you don't have
to endure the pressure of wanting
company of acting towards company of
talking when it's not necessary of somebody
when it's not necessary of somebody
while they came to see me yeah okay but
have you made them stay longer through
your incessant sort of you know speech
and so on
so you could still see that it's on you
like you are fueling the mind to Incline
towards Society towards company or you
will be removing the fuel so the mind
will start inclining towards solitude
now again you need to recognize that
that's where the line is because you can
then have also people who just
really hate others are full available
don't want to have to deal with them
so then they quote passages in solitude
because not because they're really
minding clients to a solitude mine still
inclines to its people just with ill
will so in order to not experience the
so in order to not experience the
discomfort it will you just want to be
left alone that's sometimes
understandable but it can also become like a view
but it can also become like a view
of others bother me so much just sights
of others perceptions of others I don't
want to have to deal with it
and now that's a bit too much the other
way because it's rooted in a version so
does that mean you go and seek the
company no
that means when the company is there
well I is your mind filled with your
will are you still intimately engage
with them well exactly that's what I
mean like so one is sort of overly
firming it I always try to deny it
either way it's still defined by the
company so you don't need to then seek the
so you don't need to then seek the
company to prove to yourself that you
don't hate the company but when the
company is inevitably present which will
have to happen you see is my mind now
inclining towards Solitude out of this
neutral sort of no Solitude is
beneficial for the development of the
mind and everything else or is it
because I just don't want to deal with
this I don't want to deal with this I
don't have to talk to others I just is
it ill will
if it's so well that's your problem now
it's a different type of problem but
it's nevertheless a problem
you you can't help yourself but getting
involved even just yeah so I'm sure you
can carry on avoiding the company but
now you have to do it for the right
reasons don't think that your work is
completed having avoided company on account of ill
having avoided company on account of ill
will or not wanting to be bothered don't
think your work is completed simply by
avoiding company because now you have to
deal with the ill will and being
bothered so yes avoid the company and
then deal with this then next time
companies that you will have neither
your will nor Delight in them
in case it's relevant the the agama
parallel to that City and at this point
we're divine
it says
so much shorter just says he resorts to
two types of seclusion physical
seclusion and mental seclusion
so
like it's kind of interesting in
relation to what you just said because
like even if somebody is in physical
seclusion on account of others yeah it's
exactly that yeah they're not you know
mentally secluded you're still dwell in
that company yeah
what parallel is that to this today
I don't remember precisely which number
and point number four the dumb is one
for one who is diligent not for one who
is lazy
here Baku is resolved on abandoning
unhausen qualities and acquiring
wholesome qualities his strong firm in
exertion not casting off the duty of
cultivating wholesome qualities things
things
well that I mean we covered that in so
many other talks yeah it's pretty clear
are you abandoned in what you endured
not procrastinating yeah and also like
again not not misperceiving where your
duty is really
oh yes I'm so diligent you know I do the
chores and I fold my robe perfectly and
I and I wash the ball meticulously with
like almost methodical meditation
motions and so on but that's not your
duty do you also tolerate the minor
do you also tolerate the minor
sensuality or do you make the effort to
establish the context in regards to
essential thoughts that they besetting
you do tolerate the minor will
or you also make the effort that
whenever it presents itself even a
possibility of it you also then
establish the mind the perceptions of
how this is not for your benefit it is
for your harm and do you then endure
that oh that's where the diligent is
oh that's where the diligent is
diligence is
no I'd rather just deal with it I'd
rather discreet believes and you know
polish the floor and my duty is complete
well if you're another hunt you can just
do that because yes you would have then
done all the worrying that matters but
if you're not you are just deluding
yourself let's search the address and
let's search the address and
research yeah short verse that just says
um not for not through feeble efforts
not through
um like lack of exertion is this
extinguishment to be attained relational
suffering but I find it like the The
Suitor that is going with that is that
same sort of where it um talks about
this monk who is not doing the duties
that is that are expected that he's not
participating as much in like the sewing
of the robes and everything because he
was President basically he was doing his
own Duty and that's then the exertion
that is obviously referred to it's like
the other monks who were kind of so busy
with everything else they would kind of
once more
that have been well not necessarily but
yeah you can't you don't measure it by
that but same
but same
somebody can say okay so see seclusion
is better I shouldn't do any duties
again okay start with that and then
see what the state of mind is behind it
is because you are lazy you can't even
do the menial tasks how do you how to
how do you think you're going to be
dealing with hindrances
if even sweeping the leaves is too
disturbing for your mind oh it's too
much work
it's like okay then you dip the whole
thing upside down and you're refusing to
even try to recalibrate it
so number five
this dumb is for one who is recollected
or firming mindfulness good memory not
for one who is forgetful
and what does that mean a biku is
careful prudent and has an excellent
memory of what was said and done long
ago again just in case it's relevant the the
again just in case it's relevant the the
agama defines that one slightly
differently just says he dwells in the
four establishments of mindfulness of
recollectedness yeah
if he's a satis firmly established yeah
so how is your memory
how is your memory
if we combine the two
how would you remember what was said and
done long time ago of relevance
by remembering your posture
can I just be mindful of my knees and
somehow the knowledge of what I heard a
long time ago we'll just come back
how would you remember anything
where'd you find your memory is it in
physical Sensations with your body in
the present moment right here right here
at the moment right here is that how you
remember stuff
I spoke about it before you remember by
stepping away by sort of uh or at least
temporarily stepping aside from
absorption incense objects
that's why one who is practicing virtue
sense restraint uh leading himself away
from sense objects from engagement with
the content is naturally becoming more
mindful he's naturally becoming less
forgetful and knowledgeable well exactly
now now that you're not forgetful now
that you that you are mindful that you
can recollect exactly now you have this
contexts that are becoming more and more
known so that's the the four
so that's the the four
foundations of mindfulness basically the
four uh
practices of surmounting the engagement
with the content of your experience and
Discerning the nature of it if you
engage with the content of your
experience you're not aware that you're
engaged yeah that's already lost that's
already a degree of of of lacking
perspective yeah
so you could if you could if you would
then take that thread all the way as we
said before afraid of recollectedness
well they will be in the end
impossible for you to not have
perspective upon your situation as a whole of anata
upon your situation as a whole of anata
Anita everything else that you need to
understand did you need to discern in
these five aggregates
so the only way to discern the five area
is correctly is to start withdrawing
yourself from the content of your senses
because that's not where you're going to
find them
most of the five instances abandoning
them it's directly related to
remembering things that were
said and done long ago well because if
you know if he's speaking about the
the non the things that are present in a
non-specific manner in a manner that you
cannot measure as an object of your
senses a degree of presence the five
hindrances are the chief amongst them
that's why if you were to surmount them
on that level the mind will be in Jannah
whereas the specific again is is what is
taking away from the non-pacific
specific yeah you start you start by
being taken away so then that's what
virtue has to come precepts have to come
first uh that you don't even know to what
uh that you don't even know to what
extent but by keeping the precepts and
guarding of the sensors you are sort of
withdrawing yourself gradually out of
that overly proliferated specificity of
your senses and Pleasures in avoiding
pain and so on which is all down the
rabbit holes of objects sense objects
Central proliferation fundamentally
you're in the content not because you
haven't really collected all the
information about how this comes about
no it's because you're not withdrawn
from it sufficiently enough so mentally
have you endure the pull of the senses
without acting out of it sufficiently
enough to the point that you're settled
not bothered by it regardless of which
way it takes with regardless of what
object presents itself that's how you
then dwell on the nature of the
experience which is what dhamma is the
nature so it's not it's not a mystical
or axis this nature it's like no we're
drawing yourself from the content
starting from sensuality acting out of
real will sorts of Cruelty eventually up
to the five hindrances and then you will
be the dhamma you will be the the on the
level of Discerning the nature of the
experience because you have actually
made that diligent effort to withdraw
yourself from everything else that was
obstructing it it's basically what
you're done or how you attemption it's
both to begin with
because a person can think okay I can
attend to sensuality As Long As I attend
it rightly in the sense of I am already
pulled by Central no no certain things
there's you have to avoid even certain
what's until eventually of course you have
until eventually of course you have
fully overcome the wrong type of
attention then you would not be able to
attend it in that old way that you
thought it was a neutral way from which
I can practice mindfulness now certain
things need to be stopped and abandoned
in potentiality ill will must not be
welcomed and so on
but fundamentally you want to uproot it
then yeah you have to endure those
states of mind
um
not having acted out of them so when I
say you got to deny the centrality means
you gotta deny your engagement with it
because that is what sensuality is for
you and then endure the as we said before
and then endure the as we said before
that the the discontent of of uh of the
unfulfilled desire
because you realize okay so that's one
thing but me acting on account of it
that's another thing so I should first
stop acting on account of it not being
moved by it becomes settled in regard to
it and then you stop being bothered by
it
and point number six the dumb is for one
who's settled not for one who is
unsettled summer hitter hmm
and what does that mean it means one who
is able to
attain the journalism practice John
while he was able to be
unmoved by things that would animals
move you
yeah so I and that's again brings me
back frequently to that point to the
whole samadhi thing the whole practice
of overcoming unwholesome is not about
getting rid of these unwholesome things
and being a move by them that's how you
get rid of them
when you are on move by them they'll
stop coming
because they keep coming because there's
still possibility they could move you
know Point number seven this dumb is for
one who is wise not for one who is
foolish I want to put discerns another
one done yeah yeah one with panya sermon
yeah here went wherever one goes he is
endowed with discernment that is noble
and insightful leading to the
destruction of suffering so that's all
he wherever you go you see the context
that he needs to see he protected he
maintains it
foreign to the right View
to the right View
yeah
from the start to the end yeah
so the dumbest one for the right
yeah who has the right view yeah
and point number eight is kind of
similar actually
um this dam is for one who Delights in
non-proliferation not for not for one who Delights in
not for not for one who Delights in
proliferation
he's he's one whose mind inclines
towards the ending of proliferation
becomes calm settles down and is
liberated so it's kind of saying the same you know
so it's kind of saying the same you know
you're not proliferating
those obstacles where you're not
proliferating greed acting out of greed your anger and
greed acting out of greed your anger and
your delusion yeah
so what is the like what is the
basis for any proliferation because you
could proliferate thoughts on Dharma
now that that would be the dhamma for
you at the time but you could
proliferate
you could proliferate your poly study
your scholarship you could proliferate
all these things you could proliferate
just seeking answers to the questions that
seeking answers to the questions that
are relevant to the suffering and so on
but yet you're proliferating them why
why is that what will be the difference
between somebody
um not proliferating their thoughts on
Dharma in another person proliferating
their thoughts on them
what will be there
doing it with the sense itself
okay more specifically both are doing it
with a sense of self because they're not
out of hands I only saw man is so would
be the necessary basis and what does
Ayan is always
resulting not your mistake or you
emphasize content rather than context
you and when would you do that when you
put what first
by yourself basically but when you act
out of what
desire yeah craving to understand or so
you start with craving as we said before
but the point comes when you through
starting with craving you learn that the
craving is the root of suffering so now
you're thinking the dhamma you're
clarifying the ideas you're studying
Pali but really you need to start asking
yourself is this rooted in craving
so I have doubt present in my mind about
this
is it Pleasant is it unpleasant or is it
neutral am I moved by the doubt first
yes if I am moved by the dot whatever I do
if I am moved by the dot whatever I do
including you know answering these
questions and and getting the answer
will be rooted in the hindrance of doubt
and you might do it once you do it twice
you do it 100 times but if you have any
wisdom or discernment you'll start
recognizing okay
I have provided an answer to this
countless numbers of times from all
sorts of directions
how about now I stopped that and I
endure the pain of the doubt and I don't
act out of it yeah but then everything
will fall apart and it's like well even
if everything falls apart I still know
what I will not do which is break the
precepts lose the sense of strength you
know start writing company
I'll just endure everything falling
apart because what's the definition of
because what's the definition of
everything falling apart and nothing
falling apart oh things being there on
my own terms well that's why they will
fall apart
not because there's something wrong with
them or even with my information but
because I want to hold them the way I
think they should be held
well then they should really fall apart
and they will start falling apart if you
started during the pressure of doubt and
not acting out of it and that's how the
first three factors will fall apart so craving
craving LED you to this but then craving
also made you understand and collect
information that craving is the problem
so you can now carry on perpetuating
that repetition of the same information
for the rest of your life and studying
etymology and get introduced all the
other ancient languages you know get a
degree in all of it
but fundamentally what you learn in the
very beginning the craving is a problem
you haven't dealt with it you still
haven't dealt with a craving because
you're still fueling it yeah sure not
you're not fueling it in the ways of
sensuality in the ways of uh mindless
asceticism but you are very much fueling
it in the ways of views
no so
either way you're a bombed by it you're
delighting in distracting yourself yeah
so you're not looking at that context
and that's a that is a delight in
proliferation and the word is papancha which can be
and the word is papancha which can be
like an obstacle sir proliferating
so just I mean a silly kind of question
but why would not why would I be in
Jannah by thinking these thoughts
by thinking these thoughts
why would someone might ask yeah so how
does that get so if you think this
thoughts rightly follow the thread all
the way establish your mind upon it
act accordingly yeah oh yeah yeah okay
that's that's presupposed yeah so why
wouldn't that be the genre
because I think if you're contemplating
it rightly you're not just doing a study
figuring out the poly words but actually
looking into the meaning of it you are
seeing it that you're knowing it yeah so
why are we expecting why would knowing
these things still why would knowing
these things result in John it will
pretty much
why what is John
what is John
withdrawal from what from the external
from sensuality from one wholesome state
from five hindrances from a wholesome
state so
by following these eight types of
thoughts for the ones that discern you
are fully completely surmounting
establishing the unshakable context in
regard to anything that's unwholesome
anything that can even partake in the
unhaul soon
so then Jana is like at will available
because you are perpetually outside of
the domain of unwholesome through
discernment through discernment through
enduring rightly through Discerning
through not acting out of Truth
cultivating the eight thoughts following
the thread all the way
so you are not judging whether things
are suitable or unsuitable wholesome or
wholesome buy as we said what everybody
agrees upon what majority says what the
most senior monk in the world tells you
no you're judging about whether it's
rooted in
am I seeking admiration am I seeking
sensuality am I acting out of Doubt am I
cultivating hindrances am I
proliferating my own craving through
acting out of it while I know really I
should do
that becomes your criteria and am I
diligent in regard to this criteria am I
lazy or am I putting in the work on this
level how can Janna then not be the result
how can Janna then not be the result
impossible